A Guide to the Richard Kidder Randolph Family Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Richard Kidder Randolph Family Papers 1791-1932
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
5408
707 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Richard Kidder Randolph collection was made a gift to the Library on May 10, 1988.
Scope and Content
This collection of approximately 707 documents (1791-1932) contains correspondence, business and legal papers, genealogical records, and a small amount of printed material from the Richard Kidder Randolph family, Daniel Lyman family, and Lake family. Genealogies of the Randolph family and Foote family are also included in the control folder, as is a letter from Gertrude L. (Mrs. Clinton) Merrick, which gives an overview of the correspondents in the collection. Highlights from several of the folders are noted in the following guide.
Separated Material
Second[?] page of a printed Virginia stud list [first page apparently wanting] removed from Box 3 and cataloged as a broadside.
Container List
- Business and Legal (Papers and Correspondence) of Richard Kidder Randolph: (Box Box 1)
  7 February 1812, protest re: further expansion and/or purchase of Canada by the United States.
  4 March 1834, detailed description of a plantation near Malvern Hills, Virginia. Mentions that it is situated on Turkey Island Creek (possibly the Turkey Island Plantation, the original Randolph familyhome place)
  19 December 1840, re: boundaries of Massachusetts and townships founded before 1646.
  5 March 1841, re: Whig Party politics.
  4 October 1841, 6 October 1841, 6 November 1841, letters of David Sears re: efforts to block illegal financial manoeuvres of d'Hauteville in a divorce proceeding.
  15 January 1842, n.d., letters re: Rhode Island's adoption of a written constitution and suffrage rights in voting.
  n.d., re: liberation of [Thomas Wilson] Dorr, suffrage leader in "Dorr's Rebellion". References to Mr. Whipples, the Whig Party, and the "Law and Order Party" in Rhode Island.
- Letters Sent to Richard Kidder Randolph, 1822-1835, n.d. (Box Box 1)
- Letters Sent: Daniel Lyman to Richard Kidder Randolph:, 1802-1809, 1823, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  Many references to the political climate: Mr. Rutledge's letters (1802), the Thoms Jefferson administration (1802), the Continental War in Europe (1805), the Embargo and Napoleon Bonaparte (20 August 1808, 31 January 1809).
  10 April 1809, 20 August 1809, re: establishing a cotton mill.
  26 October 1805, re: farming and drought in Newport, Rhode Island.
  12 October 1806, 18 February 1807, 18 September 1807, 20 August 1808, re: bridge construction by Daniel Lyman.
- Letters Sent: Wm[William] Berkeley to Richard Kidder Randolph, 1809 (Box Box 1)
- Correspondence Between Richard Kidder Randolph and Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph:, 1810-1846, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  Documents Richard Kidder Randolph's business travels along the East coast and Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph's domestic life.
  10 December 1810, re: liquidation of their Virginia plantation and all holdings, including slaves.
  9 February 1812, re: earthquakes "at the southward."
  28 June 1842, re: conflict resulting when Gov. [Thomas Wilson] Dorr [elected under the People's Constitution] abandoned his supporters and fled.
  n.d.[1842], 17 March 1842, 19 April 1842, re: Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph's passage by steamboat along the Ohio River, and a stage coach ride.
- Letters Sent: W[illiam] Randolph to Richard Kidder Randolph, 1811-1812 (Box Box 1)
- Letters Sent: Peyton Randolph to Richard Kidder Randolph:, 1812-1844 (Box Box 1)
  Rich collection of political items in Virginia. Includes news of the war, crops, slaves and slave sales, and elections. Persons mentioned include: John Wayles Eppes, Gedion Spencer, "Dabbs the baptist," "your old neighbour [James Madison] Maddison," H. Watkins and the "Court House gang at the (Duke of York)," Judith Randolph, Philip P[endleton] Barbour, [Martin] Van Buren, Innes [Randolph], [Andrew] Jackson.
  The following letters refer to John Randolph of Roanoke: 9 August 1812; 4 January 1827; 15 October 1812; 22 October 1827; 15 May 1813; 22 December 1827; 1 January 1816; 8 March 1837
- Letters Sent: Anne Randolph to Richard Kidder Randolph, 1815, 1822, 1829 (Box Box 1)
- Letters Sent: Wm [William] B. Randolph to Richard Kidder Randolph, 1825-1827 (Box Box 1)
- Letters Sent: Lucy H. Taylor to Richard Kidder Randolph or Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph, 1839, 1849 (Box Box 1)
- Personal Papers: [Richard Kidder Randolph]:, 1827, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  12 April 1827, copy of speech to the Grecian naval forces, "Lord Cockranes first Proclamation to the Greeks".
  n.d., "Remarks on slavery" and "A few remarks on Dr Channings famous publication on slavery" re: Dr. [William Ellery] Channing.
  n.d., speech re: science and nature.
- Resolution re: Death of Richard Kidder Randolph:, 1849 (Box Box 1)
  16 June 1849, 21 June 1849, letter and resolution from the Rhode Island circuit court.
- Diaries of Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph:, 1835-1836 (Box Box 1)
  Briefly records Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph's daily life, including books, weather, visitors, sewing.
- Business Papers: Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph:, 1849, 1852 (Box Box 1)
  15 March 1852, market description for sale of the Richard Kidder Randolph's Rhode Island farm.
- Miscellaneous Correspondence of Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph:, 1799, 1815-1876, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  3 October 1815, re: aftermath of hurricane that hit Rhode Island, and detailed description of a fashionable dress.
  1 December 1833, re: settlement of "Annarbour" [ Ann Arbour ].
  31 July 1853, re: countryside surrounding the Great Lakes [ Michigan ].
  20 October 1861, re: encampment of soldiers and calvary soldiers at Carondelet, near St. Louis, Missouri.
  13 November n.d., re: visit made to Mr. and Mrs. Smith, Mr. and Mrs. Roosevelt "at Bellevue, near Shrewsburg," New Jersey.
- Correspondence Between: Anne Maria (Lyman) and the Lyman Family:, 1802-1826, 1849, 1856 (Box Box 1)
  Richly detailed introduction to both Daniel Lyman and Richard Kidder Randolph familymembers, and their 19th century lifestyles in Oakland, Virginia, and in Newport and Providence, Rhode Island. Letters re: social scene, births, illnesses, deaths, politics, literature, sewing, spinning, wool/cotton manufacture, etc.
  19 March 1807, compares Connecticut and Virginia, Connecticut being "the most moral state in the Union."
  17 July 1808, 18 November 1808, [7 December 1808], re: the Embargo imposed by the United States government.
  12 November 1808, re: [James] Madison, [James] Monroe, [John] Randolph, etc.
  6 May 1819, re: injury to Commodore [Oliver Hazard] Perry's young son.
  10 July 1856, re: [Harriet Elizabeth Beecher] Stowe.
- Correspondence Between Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph and Margaret (Lyman) Arnold:, 1809-1857, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  Overview of family life in 19th century Virginia and Rhode Island.
- Letters Sent: William Minot to Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph, 1850-1868 (Box Box 1)
- Letters Sent: Margaret Dunnell to Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph (Box Box 1)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence Between Richard Kidder Randolph and/or Anne Maria (Lyman) and their Children:, 1834-1852 (Box Box 2)
  21 May 1842, re: settlement of Quincy, Illinois and the surrounding area.
- Miscellaneous Correspondence of Daniel Lyman Randolph:, 1823-1827 (Box Box 2)
  8 October 1823, re: fire aboard "the schooner Mexican of Philadelphia. "
  11 October 1827, re: "the Archipelago " in the Mediterranean sea.
- Correspondence re: Daniel Lyman Randolph's Naval Career:, 1821, 1824 (Box Box 2)
  Records Daniel Lyman Randolph's naval appointments at the Military Academy in Norwich, Vermont.
  18 November 1824, from William Hunter to Samuel S. Southard, Sec. of the Navy.
  22 November 1824, from M[atthew] C[albraith] Perry re: Daniel Lyman Randolph's promotion.
- Correspondence Between Richard Kidder Randolph and Daniel Lyman Randolph:, 1821-1829, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  Extensive information re: Daniel Lyman Randolph's travels and work in the Navy to the Mediterranean including a voyage, on the North Carolina under Commodore John Rodgers and his days at the academy in Norwich, Vermont; arrivals and/or departures of numerous ships; some family news. A few notes from Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph to Daniel Lyman Randolph are included.
  Letters re: John Randolph of Roanoke: 10 February 1822; 16 April 1824; 27 March 1822; 21 January 1825; 10 October 1823; 8 March 1825; 28 November 1823
  Letters re: [Matthew Calbraith] Perry: 8 March 1825; 14 March 1825; October 1825; 28 August 1826, Mrs. Calvert Perry
  27 March 1822, re: whaling aboard the George and Mary.
  3 October 1823, re: yellow fever epidemic on board the Grey Hound in Key West, Florida.
  2 April 1824, re: expansion of Fort Adams by the United States government.
  14 May 1825, October 1825, re: coal mining in Rhode Island, and canal dredging there by the Blackstone Canal Company.
  16 July 1826, re: deaths of "both Old president [John] Adams and Mr. [Thomas] Jefferson ".
  28 October 1827, detailed account of one of Daniel Lyman Randolph's tours of duty aboard the U.S.S. Warren.
  1 May 1829, re: Daniel Lyman Randolph's tour of duty aboard the U.S.S. Erie, and information re: settlement of Key West.
- Correspondence: Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph and Daniel Lyman Randolph:, 1822-1836, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  Detailed accounts of Daniel Lyman Randolph's sea travels in naval and whaling operations and information re: the Randolph family.
  Letters re: John Randolph of Roanoke: 7 November 1823; 14 January 1827
  11 February 1822, re: Daniel Lyman Randolph's appointment as Mr. Eddy discussed it with the Secretary of the Navy.
  16 November 1823, re: Daniel Lyman Randolph's tour of duty in an undeveloped region of Key West.
  14 January 1827, eyewitness account of "the re-internment of Com. [Oliver Hazard] Perry's remains...", and opposition in the South to "our Yankee President" [ John Quincy Adams ].
  10 May 1835, seven-page letter re: Daniel Lyman Randolph's travels during whaling operations and an accident at sea.
  27 April 1836, 10-page letter re: Daniel Lyman Randoph's travels in the Pacific, esp. around the Society Islands. Natives on the Marquesas island of Oura Poura, shell buying at Ulietea, fruits from Whytootacke, whaling operations, "a peace conference on Ulitea among the chiefs of Huahim, Tahaa, and Ulitea islands...," etc.
  n.d., re: a Presidential visit aboard Daniel Lyman Randolph's vessel.
- Correspondence Between Daniel Lyman Randolph and William Sullivan Randolph:, 1830, 1834, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  7 January n.d., rich account of sperm whaling operations as experienced by a whaler.
- Correspondence Between Benjamin Harrison Randolph and Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph and/or Richard Kidder Randolph:, 1827-1847, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  28 October 1827, re: Cal[?]ert Perry in Rhode Island.
  9 February 1831, re: Benjamin Harrison Randolph's passage in the snow by sleigh from Virginia to New York.
  1 April 1840, 4 February 1841, re: Politics in St. Louis, Missouri, and General Harrison.
- Miscellaneous Correspondence of Elizabeth Anne (Randolph) Perry, 1834-1846, n.d. (Box Box 2)
- Letters Sent: Elizabeth Anne (Randolph) Perry to Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph:, 1834, 1842, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  Early letters (1834) describe a lengthy visit Elizabeth Anne (Randolph) Perry made to Virginia in which she experienced and recorded southern life as seen by a young Rhode Islander. Later letters (1842, n.d.) re: Elizabeth Anne (Randolph) Perry's daily life after marriage to Oliver Hazard Perry, son of Commodore Perry. Some details re: Oliver Perry's work.
  4 March 1842, a note from Richard Kidder Randolph to Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph re: "the adoption or rejection of the Landholders constitution" in Rhode Island.
  11 [n.d.], account of Col. [ Charles Callahan or Thomas Handasyd] Perkin's house in Roxbury, which was filled with art treasures and antiques.
- Letters Sent: Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph to Elizabeth Anne (Randolph) Perry:, 1831-1847, n.d.; two folders: (Box Box 2)
  Letters re: 19th century daily life in Rhode Island as experienced by the Randolph families. Some references to the family of Com. Oliver Hazard Perry, whose son Elizabeth Anne (Randolph) Perry married.
  10 June 1838, re: friendly rendez-vous in Rhode Island between American and French navies.
  12 May 1839, re: lawsuit brought by "Uncle John" [ John Randolph of Roanoke ] against William Sullivan Randolph.
  26 June 1842, re: "rebels...encamped at Chapachet [?]" in significant numbers.
  20 August 1842, re: trials of the voting "Suffrage people" in Rhode Island.
  7 July 1844, re: flooding of "the Missisipi and other rivers..."
  15 November 1846, re: need for additional funding "to carry on the war," which "seems so unjust, unnecessary, and aggressive..." [war with Mexico ].
  9 August 1846, re: account of a steamboat ride.
  22 January 18--, re: odd case of a man who survived a suicide attempt after confessing to having committed a murder.
  12 April [ca. 1842], re: settlement of Quincy, Illinois and the surrounding area. Also mention of suffrage movement in Rhode Island.
  16 July n.d., re: problems caused by flooding of the Mississippi River.
  2 June n.d., re: wreck of the vessel the Gov. Coddington.
- Letters Sent: From O[liver] H[azard] Perry:, 1837-1854, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  Son of Com. Oliver Hazard Perry and husband of Elizabeth Anne (Randolph) Perry. Letters re: his travels and/or business.
- Miscellaneous Correspondence of John Randolph Randolph, 1829-1881, n.d. (Box Box 3)
- Business and Legal Papers/Business Correspondence of John Randolph Randolph:, 1836-1850,1872-1873, n.d. (Box Box 3)
  20 December 1836, summary report re: committee "appointed by the Providence Anti Slavery Socy " to examine slavery laws in Rhode Island.
  16 January 1847, re: money owed by Com. M[atthew] C[albraith] Perry's son.
- Letters Sent: Richard Kidder Randolph and/or Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph to John Randolph Randolph:, 1825-1852, 1872-1873 (Box Box 3)
  15 July 1825, re: John Randolph Randolph's studies at West Point.
  26 April 1831, 31 May 1831, 3 June 1831, re: John Randolph Randolph's studies at Cambridge.
  27 January 1832, re: preparations for a public hanging.
  16 March 1851, Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph explains the "event that cast the dreadful shade over J[ohn] R[andolph of Roanoke ]'s life..." A brief account of the Bizarre scandal that gives names, circumstances, and charges involved in this investigation of infanticide.
  2 October 1852, 10 October 1852, re: selling the Randolph familyfarm in Rhode Island to Jonathan Lake. Also, information re: the dispute following Betsy (Engs) Randolph's death.
  1 April 1873, re: Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph's ancestry before and during the Revolutionary War.
- Letters Sent: John Randolph Randolph to Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph and/or Richard Kidder Randolph:, 1832-1847 (Box Box 3)
  14 April 1832, re: upcoming elections in Rhode Island, [ Samuel] Arnold as a candidate.
  17 April 1834, re: political activities in Providence, Rhode Island, and John Randolph Randolph defends his plans to marry Betsy Engs.
  11 December 1837, re: steamboat ride along the Mississippi River, stage coach ride from Baltimore to Wheeling, descriptions of Wheeling, Cincinnati, Louisville. Also, bounty lands in Illinois, "given to revolutionary soldiers" by the United States government.
  9 January 1838, re: very early settlement of the Quincy, Illinois area.
  9 December 1838, re: Quincy, Illinois: as a classless society, setting up the public library, etc. Also, a vivid account of a stage coach wreck.
- Letters Sent: From Margaret Lyman Dunnell to John Randolph Randolph, 1837, 1839, 1853 (Box Box 3)
- Letters Sent: From John Randolph Randolph re: Elizabeth Anne (Randolph) Perry's Illness and Death:, 1847 (Box Box 3)
  Letters re: death of Elizabeth Anne (Randolph) Perry.
- Correspondence and Papers re: John Randolph Randolph's Dispute with Samuel Engs and Francis Lawton over Betsy (Engs) Randolph's Estate:, 1847-1860 (Box Box 3)
  Letters re: rights to Betsy (Engs) Randolph's land in Quincy, Illinois, and the care of John Randolph Randolph and Betsy (Engs) Randolph's children following her death.
- Correspondence Between John Randolph Randolph and/or Betsy (Engs) Randolph and Their Children:, 1848-1852, 1874-1878, n.d. (Box Box 3)
  22 May 1874, re: a devastating fire in downtown Central City, Colorado.
- Miscellaneous Correspondence of Betsy (Engs) Randolph, 1835-1841, n.d. (Box Box 3)
- Letters Sent: Betsy (Engs) Randolph and John Randolph Randolph to Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph:, 1838-1850, n.d. (Box Box 3)
  Letters re: early settlement of Quincy, Illinois, detailing buildings, parties, religion, family matters, etc.
  22 July 1842, re: efforts to "sustain Quincy in the County Seat Question..."
  11 October 1842, re: conversion of a local woman to Mormonism.
  27 October 1844, re: elections and voting in Quincy, including the following: "...they are quiet now, but I fear there will trouble before night.--for John says there's whiskey in great abundance; some of the country folks brought in a 'coon and killed it at the Court-house door-J said he was told that they skinned it alive..."
  n.d., re: countryside surrounding Quincy, including a detailed description of a growing Mormon settlement near Quincy.
- Letters Sent: Betsy (Engs) Randolph to John Randolph Randolph, 1840, 1848-1849 (Box Box 3)
- Letters Sent: From Thomas Lyman Randolph:, 1832-1850 (Box Box 3)
  Early letters (1832) re: Thoman Lyman Randolph's college days.
  22 March 1849, re: death of Richard Kidder Randolph.
- Letters Sent: From Julia Virginia (Randolph) Minturn:, 1839, n.d. (Box Box 3)
  26 December 1839, 5 January 1840, re: Julia Virginia (Randolph) Mintum's honeymoon in Gibralter, including descriptions of Christmas Day celebrations, excursions, islanders, the town of Malaga, etc.
- Miscellaneous Correspondence of Lucy Maria (Randolph) Breese:, 1841, 1847 (Box Box 3)
  Letters re: the illness and death of Julia Virginia (Randolph) Minturn.
- Miscellaneous Correspondence of George E. Randolph, 1852, 1872, n.d. (Box Box 3)
- Letters Sent: To Mary (Randolph) Lake and Lake Family:, 1844-1896 (Box Box 3)
  [26 October 1888], re: a bicycle parade held at night in which "the bicycles were decorated with chinese and Japanese laterns..."
  11 December 1891, re: experiences of an American family living in Berlin.
  25 May 1896, letter of Powhatan Bouldin, re: his books, including
  Home Reminiscences of John Randolph of Roanoke
  .
- Letters Sent: Richard Conover Lake to Mary (Randolph) Lake:, 1892 (Box Box 3)
  Letters from Europe re: Richard Conover Lake's excursion there with their daughter.
- Miscellaneous Correspondence:, 1803, 1834-1872, n.d. (Box Box 3)
  20 September 1857, re: the life and duties of a public school teacher in Washington, D.C.
- Miscellaneous Business and Legal Papers:, 1861, 1896, n.d. (Box Box 3)
  [1869], petition to United States attorney general E. R. Hoar for a ruling of holle prosequi in the case of " Henry Whaley of Cranston," Rhode Island, indicted of illegal distilling operations.
- Miscellaneous Papers:, n.d. (Box Box 3)
  n.d., this small card was used to attempt to secure the release of "Capt Randolph R[hode] I[sland] Artillery Keanngs Division In relation to Exchange of my brother now a prisoner of war taken at Pittsburg [signed] Ggr [George] E Randolph. " Directions on the verso give instructions to follow to secure his release.
  27 April-5 May n.d., entries from an anonymous woman's journal.
  n.d., "Memorandum about the 'Wanton' family. ..", a brief account of Edward Wanton (and his children), member of the Society of Friends and victim of religious persecution in the United States during the 1600's.
- Genealogical Records re: Richard Kidder Randolph Family and Legal Wills of Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph:, 1802, 1868, n.d. (Box Box 3)
  7 July 1802, Marriage certificate of Richard Kidder Randolph and Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph.
  n.d., "Sketch of study for R[ichard] K[idder] Randolph. .."
  n.d., records of Elizabeth Anne (Randolph) Perry and Julia Virginia (Randolph) Minturn.
  n.d., Genealogical records (2 copies) of issue of Richard Kidder Randolph and Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph.
  1868, n.d., wills of Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph.
- Genealogical Records re: Daniel Lyman Family and Legal Will of Daniel Lyman:, 1828, n.d. (Box Box 3)
  9 March 1828, will of Daniel Lyman [fragments].
  n.d., genealogical records of the Daniel Lyman family.
- Genealogical Records re: Lake Family, 1932, n.d. (Box Box 3)
- Receipts: Richard Kidder Randolph, 1844-1849 (Box Box 3)
- Receipts: Anne Maria (Lyman) Randolph, 1847-1852, 1856, n.d. (Box Box 3)
- Receipts: Miscellaneous:, 1847 (Box Box 3)
  4 August 1847, paid by O[liver] H[azard] Perry for "6 Carriages to attend in Funril..." [for Elizabeth Anne (Randolph) Perry ].
- Receipts: John Randolph Randolph from Samuel Engs and Francis Lawton, 1852-1859 (Box Box 3)
- Legal re: Family Estates: Benjamin Harrison Randolph and George Engs, 1873, n.d. (Box Box 3)
- Photographs, n.d. (Box Box 3)
- Printed Material:, 1830-187-, n.d. (Box Box 3)
  Includes one electoral ticket, ca. 1864, for Abraham Lincoln and two for George B. McClellan, presidential candidates.
  n.d., sale brochure for "The Bricksburg Tract " in New Jersey.
- Printed Material: Newspapers, 1871-1879 (Box Box 3)
- Photostats of letters. (Box Box 4)
  For a complete listing, check the control folder.
- Indenture for Daniel Lyman., 18 November 1791 (Oversize Oversize)
- Harvard diploma of Richard Kidder Randolph., 1804 (Oversize Oversize)
- Probate court account for the estate of Benjamin H[arrison] Randolph., 4 August 1873 (Oversize Oversize)